<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:linkend="http://www.w3.org/1999/linkend"
    xmlns:xref="http://www.w3.org/1999/xref"
    xmlns:wadl="http://wadl.dev.java.net/2009/02"
    version="5.0-extension RackBook-2.0" xml:id="Overview">
    <title>OpenStack API Complete Reference</title>
    <para>
        Use the OpenStack APIs and extensions to launch server instances,
        create images, assign metadata to instances and images, create
        containers and objects, and complete other actions in your OpenStack
        cloud.
    </para>
    <para>
        The API <emphasis role="bold">status</emphasis> reflects the state of
        the endpoint on the service. <emphasis role="bold"
        >CURRENT</emphasis> is a stable version that is up-to-date, recent,
        and might receive future versions. This endpoint should be prioritized
        over all others. <emphasis role="bold">SUPPORTED</emphasis> is a
        stable version that is available on the server. However, it is not
        likely the most recent available and might not be updated or might be
        deprecated at some time in the future. <emphasis role="bold"
        >DEPRECATED</emphasis> is a stable version that is still available but
        is being deprecated and might be removed in the future. <emphasis
        role="bold">EXPERIMENTAL</emphasis> is not a stable version. This
        version is under development or contains features that are otherwise
        subject to change. For more information about API <emphasis
        role="bold">status</emphasis> values and version information, see
        <link
        xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/VersionDiscovery"
        >Version Discovery</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
        You must install the packages for each API separately. You can use the
        APIs and extensions after you authenticate through the Identity API:
    </para>
    <wadl:resources xmlns:wadl="http://wadl.dev.java.net/2009/02">
        <wadl:resource
            href="../wadls/identity-api/src/v2.0/wadl/identity.wadl#tokens"
        />
    </wadl:resources>
    <para>To get started with the APIs, see the <link
            xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/api/quick-start/content/"
            >OpenStack API Quick Start</link>.</para>
</preface>
