<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" version="5.0"
    xml:id="openstack-api-quick-start">
    <title>OpenStack API Quick Start</title>
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <para>Although you install each OpenStack service separately, the
        OpenStack services work together to meet your cloud needs:
        Identity, Compute, Image service, Block Storage, Networking
        (neutron), Object Storage, Orchestration, and Telemetry. With
        the <link xlink:href="http://www.trystack.org/"
            >TryStack</link> OpenStack installation, these services
        work together in the background of the installation.</para>
    <para>After you authenticate through Identity, you can use the
        other OpenStack APIs to create and manage resources in your
        OpenStack cloud. You can launch instances from images and
        assign metadata to instances through the Compute API or the
            <command>nova</command> command-line client.</para>
    <para>To begin sending API requests, use one of the following
        methods:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">cURL</emphasis></para>
            <para>A command-line tool that lets you send HTTP requests
                and receive responses. See <xref
                    linkend="Compute_API_Quick_Start"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">OpenStack command-line
                    clients</emphasis></para>
            <para>Each OpenStack project provides a command-line
                client that enables you to access its API through
                easy-to-use commands. See <xref linkend="cli-intro"
                />.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">REST clients</emphasis></para>
            <para>Both Mozilla and Google provide browser-based
                graphical interfaces for REST. For Firefox, see <link
                    xlink:href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/restclient/"
                    >RESTClient</link>. For Chrome, see <link
                    xlink:href="http://code.google.com/p/rest-client/"
                    >rest-client</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">OpenStack Python Software
                    Development Kit (SDK)</emphasis></para>
            <para>Use this SDK to write Python automation scripts that
                create and manage resources in your OpenStack cloud.
                The SDK implements Python bindings to the OpenStack
                API, which enables you to perform automation tasks in
                Python by making calls on Python objects rather than
                making REST calls directly. All OpenStack command-line
                tools are implemented by using the Python SDK. See
                    <link
                    xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/sdk.html"
                    >OpenStack Python SDK</link> in the
                    <citetitle>OpenStack End User
                Guide</citetitle>.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <xi:include href="api-quick-start-intro.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="cli-uses.xml"/>
</chapter>
